<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>David Failing</title>
    <link>/author/david-failing/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/david-failing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>David Failing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© David Failing 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/author/david-failing/avatar_hufa8c6615e4060d829ed29d1196187f83_7063355_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>David Failing</title>
      <link>/author/david-failing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go Forth and Multiply</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-04-17-tsu-mtcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2019-04-17-tsu-mtcs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spoke to math and computer science students about how my interdisciplinary undergraduate experience helped me have a better graduate school experience, and build a career as a mathematics faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m PHRE To Do What I Want</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-02-21-phre-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2019-02-21-phre-seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spoke to PHRE 475 Senior Seminar students about how my interdisciplinary undergraduate experience helped me have a better graduate school experience, and build a career as a mathematics faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commutative, idempotent groupoids and the constraint satisfaction problem</title>
      <link>/publication/2015-algebra-universalis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2015-algebra-universalis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissertation: Commutative, idempotent groupoids and the constraint satisfaction problem</title>
      <link>/publication/2013-dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2013-dissertation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Defense: Commutative, Idempotent Groupoids and The Constraint Satisfaction Problem</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-07-05-phd-defense/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-07-05-phd-defense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Come eat some free food, learn what all the words in the event title mean, and offer moral support! After 5 long years at Iowa State, it&amp;rsquo;s time to graduate so that I can move on to&amp;hellip; more graduate school!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure Theory of CI-Groupoids of Bol-Moufang Type</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-04-28-ams-central/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-04-28-ams-central/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A groupoid identity $p \approx q$ is of Bol-Moufang type if (i) the same 3 variables appear in $p$ and $q$, (ii) one of the variables appears twice in $p$ and $q$, (iii) the remaining two variables appear once in $p$ and $q$, and (iv) the variables appear in the same order in $p$ and $q$. Phillips and Vojtechovsky studied quasigroup and loop varieties defined by one additional identity of Bol-Moufang type, showing that there are exactly 26 and 14 such varieties, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aided by Prover9/Mace4 and the Universal Algebra Calculator, we show that there are exactly eight varieties of commutative, idempotent groupoids defined by one additional identity of Bol-Moufang type. Five of them are congruence meet-semidistributive. We investigate the structure of the variety of commutative, idempotent groupoids satisfying $x(x(yz)) \approx (x(xy))z$, and show that it is the regularization of the variety of squags. We also show that every finite commutative, idempotent, distributive groupoid is a Plonka sum of quasigroups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSP for Commutative, Idempotent Groupoids</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-04-14-ams-western/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2013 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-04-14-ams-western/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A theorem of Bulatov, Jeavons and Krokhin states that when the algebra associated with a core template does not lie in a Taylor variety, then the CSP for that template is NP-complete. In the same paper, the authors conjecture that in all other cases, the corresponding CSP is solvable in polynomial time. Maroti and McKenzie showed that an algebra generates a Taylor variety if and only if it has a $k$-ary weak near-unanimity (WNU) operation for some $k$; this shifts the search for a proof of the algebraic dichotomy conjecture to focus on WNU operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A binary operation is a WNU precisely if it is commutative and idempotent, and a semilattice operation is known to be sufficient for the tractability of an algebra. Using Prover9 and the Universal Algebra Calculator, we investigate several weakenings of associativity and show that they too are sufficient for the tractability of a finite commutative, idempotent groupoid. In particular a finite CI-groupoid has a tractable CSP if it satisfies any of the following identities: $x(y(xz)) \approx x((yx)z)$, $x(y(yz)) \approx ((xy)y)z$, $x(yz) \approx (xy)(xz)$. A key tool is the theory of Plonka sums. Roughly speaking, we prove that a finite Plonka sum of finite algebras lying in a tractable variety is tractable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer-Aided Investigation of Abstract Algebras (Or, The Computer Solved My Thesis Problem...)</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-03-21-mtcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-03-21-mtcs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract Algebra is the study of axiomatically defined structures arising from concrete objects, with the aim of establishing properties of those objects. Universal Algebra, loosely construed, is the study of axiom systems for their own sake (e.g. the theory of groups). With the help of automated reasoning tools like Prover9/Mace 4 and the Universal Algebra calculator, we may rapidly generate structures which satisfy a system of axioms, or make (and test) conjectures about the axioms. The talk will be particularly accessible to students currently enrolled in Math 200 and beyond, and possible topics for future undergraduate research will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Prelim: Constraint Satisfaction Problems On Bol-Moufang CI-Groupoids</title>
      <link>/talk/2012-09-20-phd-prelim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2012-09-20-phd-prelim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Come listen to me talk about Constraint Satisfaction Problems and Bol-Moufang Groupoids! Or come heckle me from the back row! Or, just come and eat tasty snacks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Affinely self-generating sets and substitution sequences</title>
      <link>/talk/2008-12-01-isu-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2008 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2008-12-01-isu-seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kimberling defined a self-generating set $S$ of integers as follows: 1 is a member of $S$, and if $x$ is a member of $S$, then $2x$ and $4x - 1$ are in $S$. Nothing else is in $S$. As an REU project, I investigated several interesting properties of the Kimberling set, and its resulting sequences reduced modulo  m  - particularly the case  m  = 2, which yields the Fibonacci word. &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/journals/JIS/VOL10/Garth/garth14.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Garth and Gouge (2007)&lt;/a&gt; proved not only that any of a special class of affinely self-generating sets of integers reduced modulo $m$may be generated by a substitution morphism, but also its characteristic sequence, which turns out to be automatic. The talk will be introductory in nature, and will also discuss some of the open questions posed by Garth and Gouge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Generating Sets, Missing Blocks, and Substitutions</title>
      <link>/talk/2006-03-31-maa-missouri/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2006-03-31-maa-missouri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We generalize the result of Allouche, Shallit, and Skordev regarding the Kimberling sequence, defined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1$ belongs to $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the integer $x$ belongs to $S$, then $2x$ and $4x-1$ are also in $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nothing else is in $S$. Thus:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$S = 1\  2\  3\  4\  6\  7\  8\  11\  12\  14\  15\  16\ldots$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set $T=S-1$, with its first term removed, is both the set of integers whose binary expansions contain no 00 block and the fixed point of the Fibonacci morphism $0\rightarrow01$, $1\rightarrow0$. We expand this result to the natural generalization of the Fibonacci morphism, of the form $0\rightarrow0^n1$, $1\rightarrow0$&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Generating Sets, Missing Blocks, and Substitutions</title>
      <link>/talk/2005-11-12-mako/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2005 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2005-11-12-mako/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We generalize the result of Allouche, Shallit, and Skordev regarding the Kimberling sequence, defined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1$ belongs to $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the integer $x$ belongs to $S$, then $2x$ and $4x-1$ are also in $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nothing else is in $S$. Thus:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$S = 1\  2\  3\  4\  6\  7\  8\  11\  12\  14\  15\  16\ldots$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set $T=S-1$, with its first term removed, is both the set of integers whose binary expansions contain no 00 block and the fixed point of the Fibonacci morphism $0\rightarrow01$, $1\rightarrow0$. We expand this result to the natural generalization of the Fibonacci morphism, of the form $0\rightarrow0^n1$, $1\rightarrow0$&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
