<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>David Failing</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>David Failing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© David Failing 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu2fefdda865d4d5c2e240ee6c853294a4_26624_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>David Failing</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>/cv/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cv/experience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accomplishments</title>
      <link>/cv/accomplishments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cv/accomplishments/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Go Forth and Multiply</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-04-17-tsu-mtcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2019-04-17-tsu-mtcs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spoke to math and computer science students about how my interdisciplinary undergraduate experience helped me have a better graduate school experience, and build a career as a mathematics faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Careers in Mathematics</title>
      <link>/2019/02/21/careers-in-mathematics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2019/02/21/careers-in-mathematics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at &lt;a href=&#34;http://tvazzana.sites.truman.edu/careers-in-mathematics/&#34;&gt;Careers in Mathematics&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Failing&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;
Assistant Professor of Mathematics  &lt;br/&gt;
Lewis University  &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bachelor’s degree in Mathematics and Philosophy &amp;amp; Religion with with minors in Asian Studies and International Studies in 2008&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PhD in Mathematics from Iowa State University in 2013&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Master’s degree in Library and Information Science at the University of Illinois (in progress)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to be a math major at Truman in large part because math was easy for me in high school, up to and including AP Calculus. I also had a knack for explaining concepts to others (not just in mathematics), so I wanted to teach high school mathematics. Eventually, that morphed into a career in teaching mathematics at the college level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current Position:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an Assistant Professor of Mathematics and Director of the Scholars Academy (honors program) at Lewis University in Romeoville, IL. I grew up in the Chicago suburbs, so I targeted the location in particular as a way to be closer to my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How I use math in my job:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the obvious (it’s the subject I teach), I also conduct original research in Universal Algebra, studying algebraic properties of certain computational problems that determine if their solution is either easy or hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advice for students getting ready to hit the job market or apply to graduate school:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are headed for graduate school in mathematics, take the GRE subject test seriously. Not all programs require it these days, but the majority of the material will come from courses you either took as a senior in high school or early in your undergraduate career, so you’ll want to brush up on it. Find a way to use your Truman experience to stand out from other applicants. I was a teaching assistant for Dr. Lloyd Pflueger in PHRE for nearly 3 years, and that provided experience for a funded TA job in graduate school. Having a double major in a non-science field made me a stronger communicator of complex ideas as well, so I would recommend highlighting unusual areas of your undergraduate experience that make you uniquely qualified for your target program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m PHRE To Do What I Want</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-02-21-phre-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2019-02-21-phre-seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spoke to PHRE 475 Senior Seminar students about how my interdisciplinary undergraduate experience helped me have a better graduate school experience, and build a career as a mathematics faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview: Professor David Failing, Lewis University</title>
      <link>/2018/04/10/interview-professor-david-failing-lewis-university/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2018/04/10/interview-professor-david-failing-lewis-university/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at &lt;a href=&#34;https://theiblblog.blogspot.com/2018/04/interview-professor-david-failing-lewis.html&#34;&gt;The IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a Q&amp;amp;A interview with Professor David Failing, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lewisu.edu/facstaffdirectory/FacStaffDirDetails2.htm?emp_id=2286&amp;amp;last=&amp;amp;dept_id=&amp;amp;box=&amp;amp;campus_id=&amp;amp;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lewis University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor David Failing has been using IBL methods for the past few years, and recently posted on instagram a nice letter he received from a student about learning to be more comfortable presenting math to classmates and how that impacts their level of engagement. Professor Failing is an avid runner of ultra marathons, and one of the bloggers on &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks for joining us today on the IBL Blog! We’d really like to hear about a positive note you had with a student from your fall Linear Algebra class. Could you share what your student wrote and tell us more about how this student got to this point?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just one week in to the spring 2018 semester, I received an email from a student who is currently taking Discrete Mathematics with me, and had taken my Linear Algebra course in the past fall semester. The student is a graduating senior in computer science, and while they are an A student, expressed some concerns in the fall about how the material was being presented, and how at times they didn’t “get it” right away when examples were shared in class without a lot of time for discussion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi Dr. Failing,  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I just wanted to take a second to say how much better I think this semester is going to be with the presentation-style course! I was hesitant with the idea at first, but I think everyone in the class is much more alert during class and open to learning this way. In addition, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have notes that are not too overwhelming in the amount of information given to us each day.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Also, if the peanut gallery of us who haven&amp;rsquo;t presented yet are getting another chance, I&amp;rsquo;d like to attempt at presenting tomorrow :)  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Thanks,  &lt;br/&gt;
Fall 2017 Linear Algebra Student&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you teach your fall Linear Algebra class?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Linear Algebra course in the fall was one of the largest I’ve ever taught - starting with 38 students. Previously, I had used David Clark’s Linear Algebra notes from the Journal of Inquiry Based Learning in Mathematics with a 2-person course I taught for math majors. This time around, my course had to meet the needs of several constituencies - mathematics, computer science, chemistry, and physics. I chose to conduct the course “interactive lecture” style, building Beamer slide decks for each of the sections we covered from David Lay’s “Linear Algebra and Its Applications,” anticipating that I would record YouTube lectures in the future to conduct a flipped class. I peppered the slides with lots of “Think-Pair-Share” activities and examples we would work out on the board as a class, aside from the usual selection of definitions, examples, and major theorems. Students did some online homework in MyMathLab after I lectured, and once a week they&amp;rsquo;d turn in 2 problems per section as written work. The online HW was computational, the written would be more &amp;ldquo;proofy.&amp;ldquo;The classroom dynamic was high energy, even at a 9am time slot, and student evaluations were high at the end of the term. The approach worked out in the end, but largely because the students were attentive, stayed on top of the online HW, and asked lots of insightful questions in class.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You just started at Lewis University. Tell us what some of the factors you considered&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I left my previous institution, where I was ultimately the only tenure-track faculty member by my third year, with the intent of joining a larger department at another liberal arts university, to find more support and time for work outside the classroom. At Lewis, I saw a growing department, joint with computer science, where innovative pedagogies were supported, and the curriculum was being retooled to be more research- and project-driven. I also grew up in the Chicagoland area, so returning home was a big motivator.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you teaching this spring term (2018) and how are you teaching the course?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This spring, I’m teaching Applied Probability and Statistics, Advanced Linear Algebra, and two sections of Discrete Mathematics (meeting 4 days a week, with about 20 students apiece). I’m viewing Discrete as an “introduction to proof” type course for computer science majors, who are the majority of my students both sections. Ellie Kennedy (Northern Arizona University) shared a set of IBL course notes for discrete mathematics with me after the 2015 IBL Conference in Austin (which I was able to attend due, in part, to a small grant from AIBL). They had been passed down to her through Ted Mahavier, Jackie Jensen-Vallin and a few others. I was impressed with the problem sequence, but hadn’t had a place to use it until now. This semester, my students are working 2-5 problems from the sequence for class each day, and volunteering to present them at the board. I collect their write-ups at the end of the hour for a completion grade, and we are also having three “Proof Workshops” throughout the semester that will lead to their producing a drafted and revised Proof Portfolio representative of the techniques and topics we encounter this semester. It’s my first full-on IBL course at Lewis, and I look forward to iterating it in the future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your future plans related to teaching and IBL?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I plan to continue teaching with “big tent” IBL throughout the rest of my career, focusing on full blown proof-and-presentation courses at the upper level, but adapting to include more “traditional” lecturing when the course merits. I actually could use a more experienced practitioner as a mentor - it would be good to have regular meetings with someone to talk about the particular difficulties that one encounters in selecting “teacher moves.” What happens if the students have nothing to present one day? What happens if the class is low energy? What happens if it looks like you won’t cover the full set of materials by the end of the term? I am slated to teach Linear Algebra again in the fall, and I have a good idea of how I’ll modify the course further to make it more rewarding for the students. However, I’ve also got a few new preparations - Theories of Geometry and Abstract Algebra. Both have some good materials out there (David Clark’s text for Euclidean Geometry and Dana Ernst’s notes for Abstract are my target materials at this point), but I’ll need to adapt or supplement them to meet our own learning outcomes at Lewis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Am I? What Am I Running For?</title>
      <link>/2017/05/09/who-am-i-what-am-i-running-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/05/09/who-am-i-what-am-i-running-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first on my old blog, the now-defunct &amp;ldquo;David Explores Illinois Trails.&amp;rdquo;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you live in Illinois (and even if you don’t) then you are likely aware that our state budget is forever in decline. As a result, the very public lands where we enjoy trail use are increasingly reliant on private funds, and the work of volunteers to maintain the trails and parks statewide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first significant experience with our state’s trails came in late 2014 – I decided it was time to finally see what trail and ultra running was all about. Having just recently moved to Quincy, I visited each state park within an hour’s drive, talked to park staff about their trails and ran to explore. I also met the Flatlander Ultrarunners In Chicagoland, and joined them for my first group trail run that October. After that first 10 mile loop at Bullfrog Lake, I was hooked, and told just about anyone who would listen that “I finally found my sport!” And more importantly, I discovered that there are so many wonderful places to explore right in my own backyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trails for Illinois is a non-profit whose mission is to improve the accessibility to and conditions of our local trails, and helping locals be more aware of these beautiful resources right outside their own front door. Every home is a trailhead! This year, they are helping towns along the Hennepin Canal State Trail improve their connections to the trail, and teaching them how to use the trail to boost tourism and improve quality of life. To support the efforts of Steve Buchtel and the rest of the Trails for Illinois crew, I joined their 2017 fundraising campaign alongside my attempt at the Hennepin Hundred trail race. I’m running at Hennepin to challenge myself, but also to challenge each of you to help improve the trail, and to get out and explore it yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I joined the campaign, though, one of my bucket list items kept gnawing at me. Ever since that first trip to the trails, I’ve wanted to visit all of Illinois’ state parks and recreation areas (there are over 100 of them). But even the few parks I’ve visited near Quincy (I’ve spent over 100 hours on the trails at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.illinois.gov/dnr/Parks/Pages/SiloamSprings.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Siloam Springs State Park&lt;/a&gt;) are in desperate need of maintenance, both on and off the trails. A single fundraising campaign as I train for a single 100 mile trail race won’t even begin to show my appreciation for the public lands where I train and race. From this, a plan was hatched to continue my fundraising efforts alongside some serious investment of effort on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illinois is now home to six 100 mile trail races. Each and every one is hosted on publicly owned lands. The majority of my training and other recreation takes place on these same lands. Why not combine the two? From October 7, 2017 to October 6, 2018, I will attempt to run all six of these 100 mile races, raising funds for Trails for Illinois throughout. This blog will chronicle my race experiences, and to feed my (and your) sense of adventure, I’ll also write about my exploration of the state’s public lands. My goal along the way will be to encourage you all to explore this great state, and to donate your time and money to the cause, while providing a trail and travel guide to the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The six races I’ll be attempting to complete as part of this challenge are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hennepinhundred.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hennepin Hundred&lt;/a&gt;, 10/7/2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?eid=4397&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tunnel Hill 100&lt;/a&gt;, 11/11/2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?eid=2833&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Potawatomi Trail Runs&lt;/a&gt;, 4/6/2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://crymearivertrailruns.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cry Me A River Trail Runs&lt;/a&gt;, 7/7/2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?eid=6129&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shawnee Hills 100&lt;/a&gt;, 8/25/2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ultrasignup.com/register.aspx?eid=2003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Farmdale Trail Run&lt;/a&gt;, 10/6/2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to sharing my adventures with all of you, and hope to hear your thoughts along the way!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grace In The Struggle</title>
      <link>/2016/11/08/grace-in-the-struggle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2016/11/08/grace-in-the-struggle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the collaborative site &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/11/08/david-grace-in-the-struggle/&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;When every day seems the same, it is because we have stopped noticing the good things that appear in our lives.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my students shared this quote from Paulo Coelho as part of her reflection on &lt;a href=&#34;http://mathyawp.blogspot.com/2013/01/the-lesson-of-grace-in-teaching.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Lesson of Grace in Teaching&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, the MAA Haimo Teaching Award Lecture (subsequently shared as a blog post) given by Francis Su at the AMS/MAA Joint Math Meetings on January 11, 2013. At this point in the semester, it can be easy for faculty and students alike to feel overwhelmed, overworked, and potentially &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chronicle.com/article/the-40-year-old-burnout/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;burned out&lt;/a&gt;. We may have tried something new in the classroom (a first foray into IBL, or a tweak to an old standby activity) and had it fail miserably. Our students might have bombed their midterm despite feeling like they&amp;rsquo;ve worked their absolute hardest in the first half of the semester. It might feel like these failures are judgements of our worth, but we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t lose sight of the good things taking place in our classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this same point in the Spring 2016 semester, I thought my students could use a little boost to their morale. Francis&#39; words had inspired me before, so I hoped the effect would be similar for them. All I asked was that, in exchange for a small boost to their grade on our most recent exam (in all courses I was teaching at the time), they read and reflect on the post. A half page minimum. My post on Facebook, from February 3, 2016:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Early reflections on Grace coming in from my students, and they are giving me confidence that I&amp;rsquo;m doing SOMETHING right this semester. Several students have commented that they need to share the post with their friends, because they see them already stressing out over their performance as if it is life or death. Several commented that they personally aren&amp;rsquo;t worried about if they make an error in class, because it&amp;rsquo;s okay! One quote from a student below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;There were also two specific times in this post that I saw how you use grace when we are in your class, the first time is when they mention names and how you were determined to learn all of our names and probably now know each and every one of us. The second was today in class, even though when they wrote their answers up on the board, instead of straight out saying that they were wrong, you explained to all of us how they got that answer, and then took the time with them to fix it to where they learned it, without making them feel embarrassed, and that meant a lot to me and showed me that I know I can come to you with my questions and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be embarrassed.&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was overjoyed that my students (from freshmen on up to seniors) were willing and able to reflect on the semester in a meaningful way. The following day, I got to work on developing the reflection assignments that this series of posts has shared throughout the fall. Since this was originally successful without much guidance, I kept the assignment simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please read the blog post (or listen to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/W4gyD0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;audio version&lt;/a&gt; linked at the top of the post) and write a 1.5-2 page reflection responding to it. Have you encountered any situations in your life where someone has given you grace as Francis Su&amp;rsquo;s advisor did? Have you given grace in a similar fashion? Just respond to the post in whatever way you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were a lot more varied than I remembered from last time. Some students said that they were very moved by reading or listening. They admitted to things like depression, abuse, homelessness, or divorce, illness or death of a family member, and how someone unexpected stepped in to their life to help them cope when it interfered with their academics. How that person gave them grace,  (or as one student shared) &amp;ldquo;comfort and stability when they have neither in their lives.&amp;rdquo; Some students, however, didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to &amp;ldquo;get&amp;rdquo; the point of my sharing the post. In fact, some students were defiant. &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t believe in grace. … I believe that everything that I receive is the result of my actions and I somehow deserved it,&amp;rdquo; one wrote. Others simply summarized Francis&#39; words, and made no apparent effort to find examples of grace in their own life. Our previous reflection assignments had a purpose I made clear at the outset – the math autobiography was meant to help us understand where they had come from, and where they were heading academically; the growth mindset activity was meant to help them think more clearly about their own learning. But grace? What the heck does that have to do with mathematics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was lost, this time around, was that I did not share my own reflection beforehand. In the spring semester, I told my classes how I have several folks in mathematics education that I look up to, Francis being one of them. That who he is (a Christian) informs what he does in the classroom, unashamedly so, and I strive for the same. I&amp;rsquo;m an educator and an outdoor athlete. I run ultramarathons (races greater than 26.2 miles, often on hiking trails in the woods) as a way to explore the world around me and to explore within. And, when I&amp;rsquo;m ready to give up, somehow I&amp;rsquo;ve always been able to dig in and persevere. Like Francis, I was ready to give up on my PhD before it was completed; I also wanted to quit, 50 or so miles in to my first 100 mile race this October. Knowing that the reward for perseverance, for sticking with what I had worked so hard to train for, was so much greater than what I stood to lose by not trying, allowed me to decide &amp;ldquo;I signed up for this, I&amp;rsquo;m going to do everything in my power to finish.&amp;rdquo; What I want to bring to the classroom is an attitude that helps my students keep sight of their goals, even when they face adversity in the interim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be the first to admit, when a student doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to &amp;ldquo;get&amp;rdquo; an assignment I&amp;rsquo;ve given, mathematical or otherwise, I take it personally. I ask myself what I did &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; or differently that caused the outcome to be different than expected. In this case, not a single one of my students commented on how they had received grace in our class. I certainly don&amp;rsquo;t give the assignment to receive pats on the back for doing good things for my students, but I had to wonder. Did I learn my students&#39; names as well this semester as I have in the past? Did I give them my very best every day? Definitely not. Have I let my own frustration with what&amp;rsquo;s gone on outside of class bleed in to my own classroom and office hours? Certainly. What I, as an instructor, need at this point in the semester, is to remind myself of the things that prompted me to share Francis&#39; speech with my students in the first place. That I need to &lt;em&gt;give myself&lt;/em&gt; grace now and again. Grace has no regard for accomplishments or titles. My students proved wise in this area. &amp;ldquo;Pass or fail you&amp;rsquo;re still a person and you can always try again,&amp;rdquo; one wrote. Grace is a tool that you can use to help you forgive yourself! While I might not be happy with how the last few reflections have gone, I can try each one again next semester, tweaking them and being sure to give my students the grace of acknowledging the failures I&amp;rsquo;ve had along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Having The Right Mindset</title>
      <link>/2016/10/23/having-the-right-mindset/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2016/10/23/having-the-right-mindset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the collaborative site &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/10/23/david-having-the-right-mindset/&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the Fall 2016 semester, my Applied College Algebra students will write five short (1-3 page) reflections, each worth 3% of the overall grade (replacing the 15% I used to allot for attendance). Most of these reflections will ask students to read an article or blog post, or watch a YouTube video, and then respond to a writing prompt. My posts this semester will focus on the results of making this change, and I will also share the full PDF and TeX files of all five assignments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We began the semester by &lt;a href=&#34;http://danaernst.com/setting-the-stage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;setting the stage&lt;/a&gt;, outlining as a group the features required of a course to allow productive failure to happen. With that completed, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/09/05/david-encouraging-introspection/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;first reflection&lt;/a&gt; was a math autobiography that helped my students identify their own attitudes and behaviors with respect to mathematics. As the first month of our semester wound down, I tasked them with a bit of a meta-reflection, adapted from a mindset activity created by Laurie Zack at High Point University: Watch a TED talk about growth mindset, and read a short article (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.businessinsider.com/being-good-at-math-is-not-about-natural-ability-2013-11&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“I’m Not A Math Person” Is No Longer A Valid Excuse&lt;/a&gt;), then reflect on the role of mindsets in their lives. My hope was to help them think more clearly about their own thinking, and to empower them to make small changes in attitude that could have a big impact on their future early in their college careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is often the case, my students provided some unexpected insights – some presented the difference between a fixed and a growth mindset as a contrast of “am I smart” versus “how can I become smarter?” Others, though, explained that a fixed mindset was a belief that they were “good enough as is,” while growth was a willingness to improve. Is it possible to be willing to improve while not actually believing you have the capacity? Largely, my students related that the fixed mindset results from judgement, a worry about looking smart, and a stubborn unwillingness to change; a growth mindset, on the other hand, they said required their striving to improve, willingly enter a state of discomfort, and work hard to reach their maximum potential. Another gem that one student presented was a view of “regular failure” versus “productive failure.” Regular failure is, as they put it “one and done,” where you give up and move on. Productive failure, on the other hand, occurs “when we spin failure and make the mishap into a positive.” While I don’t expect to use #rf in place of #pf anytime soon, it made me smile to see that at least one student “got it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seemed to be some misunderstanding on what exactly the mindsets were applied towards (ability to affect change in themselves versus actual knowledge they possessed), and I wondered if I should have explicitly told them in the assignment instructions what the growth and fixed mindsets were defined as. The “I’m Not A Math Person” article refers to incremental and entity orientations, and while the connection to mindsets was obvious to me, I don’t believe the connection was apparent to my students. The entire exercise made it clear to me that as an instructor, I need to re-read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Carol-S-Dweck/dp/0345472322&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Carol Dweck’s book&lt;/a&gt; before attempting a more detailed discussion of mindsets with my students. Perhaps, too, a pre-reflection (but post-viewing) discussion designed to come up with a “class definition” of the mindsets would help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to providing opportunities for reflection to my students, my hope with these writing assignments was that throughout the semester I would gain insight into my own teaching style. What I have been repeatedly reminded of in recent semesters is that active learning, IBL, writing assignments, and other “non-computational” activities are not magic. Student buy-in is required (which is why I use the Setting The Stage activity each semester), as is a lot of continued energy and effort on my part to maintain that buy-in. Goals (both content-related and “big picture”) need to be set, and activities carefully designed to move toward those goals. Where I could do better as an instructor, I feel, is with that continued buy-in piece. Other than showing them videos about productive failure and such throughout the semester (&lt;a href=&#34;http://theiblblog.blogspot.com/2016/06/10-videos-on-productive-failure-playlist.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stan Yoshinobu has a good list here&lt;/a&gt;), what else can I do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Feel free to download and modify the &lt;a href=&#34;./noviceiblblog/reflections/reflection2assignment.tex&#34;&gt;TeX&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;./noviceiblblog/reflections/reflection2assignment.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; of this reflection as you see fit. If you use it in your courses, send me an email at david.failing at gmail.com and let me know how it goes.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encouraging Introspection</title>
      <link>/2016/09/05/encouraging-introspection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2016/09/05/encouraging-introspection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the collaborative site &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/09/05/david-encouraging-introspection/&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/08/16/liza-treating-our-young-adult-college-students-like-we-treat-adults/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Liza&lt;/a&gt;, I have been absent from blogging for quite some time. After last year’s “Summer of IBL,” where I attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://legacyrlmoore.org/Reports/201506/program.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Legacy of RL Moore Conference&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inquirybasedlearning.org/?page=IBL_Workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IBL Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maa.org/meetings/mathfest-archive&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MathFest&lt;/a&gt; (driving cross-country as I did), this summer I spent more time focused on single-course preparation. In particular, now that I’ve taught a few IBL-based upper division courses, I wanted to add value to the two sections of Applied College Algebra I teach each fall. Susan Crook and I co-organized a Themed Contributed Paper Session (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maa.org/meetings/mathfest/program-details/2016/themed-contributed-paper-sessions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Encouraging Early Career Teaching Innovation&lt;/a&gt;) at Mathfest 2016 in Columbus, and several of the talks in our session focused on ideas that could be implemented in one course, one semester at a time. What interested me most was the idea of asking my students to spend more time on activities that aren’t just doing mathematics. A few of the talks I attended at Mathfest focused on student writing, and after I spent some time with Nick discussing his experience with &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/08/09/nick-some-ibl-things-for-my-summer-class/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;short writing assignments in a summer class&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to implement them in Applied College Algebra. Over the course of the semester, my students will write five short (1-3 page) reflections, each worth 3% of the overall grade (replacing the 15% I used to allot for attendance). Most of these reflections will ask students to read an article or blog post, or watch a YouTube video, and then respond to a writing prompt. My next few posts will focus on the results of making this change, and I will also share the full PDF and TeX files of all five assignments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each course I teach now begins with a version of Dana Ernst’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://danaernst.com/setting-the-stage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Setting The Stage&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; activity, asking students to lay out the necessary features of a course that will allow them to fail productively. Our enrollment at Quincy hovers around 40% athletes, so it usually isn’t difficult to get students to discuss the role of practice in the learning process. As a natural extension of this first day activity, I asked my students to write a math autobiography for their first reflection of the semester, due the second day of class. The assignment I developed was mostly the same as was outlined at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://maamathedmatters.blogspot.com/2016/01/math-autobiography.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MAA’s Math Ed Matters blog in January 2016&lt;/a&gt;, but I also pulled in additional questions from similar assignments by &lt;a href=&#34;http://wac.colostate.edu/aw/teaching/reisch2000/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christopher Reisch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artofmathematics.org/blogs/cvonrenesse/mathematical-autobiographies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christine von Renesse&lt;/a&gt;. I also made sure to ask my students to include at least one nonacademic obstacle they would face this semester, an idea taken from Francis Su’s “To The Mathematical Beach,” (&lt;a href=&#34;http://digital.ipcprintservices.com/publication/?i=260736&amp;amp;pre=1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FOCUS, p. 18-19&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then spent our second day of class in small groups discussing their answers. I bounced from group to group listening in, but made a point of asking each group their thoughts on what it means to be good at math. Often, students would say that this meant being faster than others, getting things right the first time when solving problems (and with no outside help), and being able to fix errors easily. What surprised me, however, was what they had to say in their essays. A handful suggested that understanding and general problem solving ability, rather than pure number sense, was the key. One student wrote that “My ability in math is only as good as my effort.” Another section of the assignment asks students to describe their learning style, including how they think they learn best, their attitude toward groupwork, and what to do when they get stuck. Some students believed that working with others can be a hindrance, while some shared their belief that this is an advantage because others can be both a source of help and an outlet for us to demonstrate our own understanding by offering assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’m not sure of, at this point, is what to do with the information I get from these reflections. Like &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2016/08/09/nick-some-ibl-things-for-my-summer-class/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nick&lt;/a&gt;, I wonder the best way to share the results with the entire class while respecting individual privacy. I have told my students that the reflections will give me insight into what they need when they are struggling – specifically the nonacademic obstacles and their ideas of what makes a good mathematics instructor. I will ask my students to return to these autobiographies at the end of the term, in hopes that they will notice areas of personal growth. Since the course mostly serves first-semester freshmen, I also hope they are encouraged toward introspection in future courses as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you done to bring reflective writing into your courses? Have you used a math autobiography or similar assignment? What did you learn about your students, and how (if at all) did you act on that information? Please share your thoughts in the comments – IBL is nothing if not a community of practice, and I hope my posts this semester provide a forum for learning from our collective experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Feel free to download and modify the &lt;a href=&#34;./noviceiblblog/reflections/reflection1assignment.tex&#34;&gt;TeX&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;./noviceiblblog/reflections/reflection1assignment.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; of this reflection as you see fit. If you use it in your courses, send me an email at david.failing at gmail.com and let me know how it goes.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>External Project</title>
      <link>/projects/external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internal Project</title>
      <link>/projects/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Many Voices Are Greater Than One</title>
      <link>/2015/10/12/many-voices-are-greater-than-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/10/12/many-voices-are-greater-than-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the Mathematical Association of America blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://maamathedmatters.blogspot.com/2015/10/many-voices-are-greater-than-one.html&#34;&gt;Math Ed Matters&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that talking to yourself can be a &lt;a href=&#34;https://gizmodo.com/talking-to-yourself-makes-you-smarter-5903023&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sign of intelligence&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-squeaky-wheel/201405/why-you-should-start-talking-yourself&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;lower stress&lt;/a&gt;. The down side is that you don&amp;rsquo;t tend to hear a lot of new ideas.  Perhaps it is best to work out ideas by yourself and, once you get stuck, find new ideas by talking to others. Though this is a simple way to describe how discovery happens in a community setting, and describe expectations for students in our classes, it has not always been a common approach to teaching. It was certainly not how we were taught to do mathematics. However, what helped many mathematicians to learn and love mathematics might not work for our students. If you could learn by just being told things, then children would never have to be told twice to brush their teeth or wash their hands. If you have ever seen a tablet or phone screen after an eight year old has used it, you know that the lesson on washing hands doesn’t stick. How do we get mathematics to stick in our students&#39; minds like grime on an eight year old’s hands? In order to make lasting knowledge, you need to get in there, explore, and experiment with everything you see, much like a child at play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a shame that so many students never get their hands dirty working with math, but rather most view mathematics as an adversary. A simple measure of this is to ask them “When was the last time math really made sense?” Even good students may have progressed without making sense of any of the ideas that make math so interesting to us. They have had excellent training in finding answers, when faculty think they should have been sense-making instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo credit Stan Yoshinobu
How do we bridge the gap between where we want our students to be and where they are now, while accounting for their lack of preparation in mathematical thinking? The good news is that you can guide your students to build a solid foundation and connect to the most important ideas in education. Key to this approach are the multitude of voices that need to be included in the conversation. If the goal of a class is for students to develop a deep understanding and appreciation of mathematics, then the students&#39; voices are even more necessary than their instructor&amp;rsquo;s. And lasting changes in the lives and minds of our students are exactly what we are trying to achieve as educators. Outside voices are also necessary: the many other like- minded educators, including past, present, and future, and in all disciplines, have to collaborate to decide how to address the ever-changing needs of our students. Faculty at many institutions are already implementing active methods of engaging students and fostering lasting learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 10 years, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inquirybasedlearning.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academy of Inquiry Based Learning&lt;/a&gt; has run a workshop to aid mathematics educators in implementing inquiry based learning (IBL). This summer, about 40 faculty, including all three authors, attended a four day workshop in beautiful San Luis Obispo. At the workshop, we worked with experienced faculty to develop materials, and individualized approaches to implementing IBL in our classrooms. This was an immersive experience into the practice and methods of “big tent IBL”, which is a broad and inclusive version of this active learning philosophy. IBL is being implemented in all manner of classes, not just upper level proof-based mathematics courses. In fact, the largest groups of people at the workshop were working on implementing IBL into the sequence of mathematics classes for elementary education majors and intermediate and college algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four day workshop also introduced us to the community of faculty across the country that want nothing more than to help others get the most out of the time spent with their students. It was just enough time to get energized and get to know a lot of great people, as well start thinking about the myriad of ways to implement IBL. Unfortunately, this was not nearly enough time to fully figure out how we would carry out these ideas in our upcoming classes. The workshop wisely includes a year of follow up mentoring with the organizers. As a way to expand on these mentoring conversations, several of us decided to write about our early experiences at &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;. Already, blogging has been a wonderful reflective exercise in connecting what we are trying in the classroom to the changes we want for students. Writing posts provides an opportunity to struggle with new pedagogical tools, and learn how to effectively communicate in a new forum. This struggle has helped us each appreciate the difficulties that our students face when grappling with new material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogging has also helped us appreciate how difficult it can be to do new things. Especially when the new thing is a fundamental change in how you approach your job. Just as when our students are learning, it’s important to have many voices for ideas and support. Our blog is about support, not just for its authors, but for anyone trying IBL or anything new in the classroom (and not just at the post-secondary level). So, &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;come visit our blog&lt;/a&gt;, participate in the discussions and learn about inquiry based learning along with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Liza Cope, David Failing, and Nick Long&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liza Cope is an Assistant Professor at Delta State University and can be contacted at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lcope@deltastate.edu&#34;&gt;lcope@deltastate.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Failing is an Assistant Professor at Quincy University and can be contacted at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:failida@quincy.edu&#34;&gt;failida@quincy.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Long is an Associate Professor at Stephen F. Austin State University and can be contacted at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:longne@sfasu.edu&#34;&gt;longne@sfasu.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Checklist - Setting Up Your IBL Course</title>
      <link>/2015/09/02/the-checklist-setting-up-your-ibl-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/09/02/the-checklist-setting-up-your-ibl-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the collaborative site &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2015/09/02/the-checklist-setting-up-your-ibl-course/&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the latter half of the IBL Workshop at Cal Poly, the organizers guided each participant toward having a few takeaways from that week’s work. Stan simply referred to this as “The Checklist” (pictured) and Liza, Nick and myself think this will be a good theme for our next series of posts. As you can see, the topics are some that we have touched on in our introductions (&lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2015/08/19/getting-things-started/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nick&lt;/a&gt; referred to writing some of his own materials, &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2015/08/24/the-power-of-student-presentations/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Liza&lt;/a&gt; to assessment techniques), but these are some of the issues a novice IBL-er must contend with as they set up their first courses. I’ll split my own posts as one for each of these topics, though others may divide up the checklist differently. Look for the series to continue over the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said once before that IBL is a community, and this blog is to be an extension of that community into the virtual space. As with any of our posts, I hope to see others chime in below in the comments section. Do you have an idea for a new post? A response to one of the ideas broached? An experience to share? Please do!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An IBLer Is Born</title>
      <link>/2015/08/22/an-ibler-is-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/08/22/an-ibler-is-born/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- This post first appeared at High Country News and is republished here with permission.--&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This post first appeared at the collaborative site &lt;a href=&#34;https://noviceiblblog.wordpress.com/2015/08/22/18/&#34;&gt;A Novice IBL Blog&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every good blog needs an origin story. So, before I start sharing my struggles and successes in adopting an Inquiry Based Learning approach to my courses, I thought it best to back up a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began to consider an IBL approach as a graduate student (in early 2013) when Ron Taylor presented a colloquium at Iowa State University on Active Learning strategies. I had always been under the impression that such approaches sacrificed the all-important “coverage.” Too many of my colleagues, however, had taken an interest in the approach for me to ignore it. Ron’s talk emphasized that IBL in particular is a commitment to teaching by letting students discover the power of their own minds, paced by student progress. Perhaps most importantly, we (as instructors) get real-time feedback from the students about how they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to MathFest 2014 in Portland, OR. I was just starting my first full time teaching position at Quincy University, and was in Portland to kick off my Project NExT fellowship (I’m a Gold ’14 dot). I ran into Ron for the first time since we’d met in Iowa, and we started talking about IBL, as well as the TeXas Style Introduction to Proof notes that he had coauthored with Patrick Rault. Ron mentioned that there were small grants available through the Academy for Inquiry Based Learning to help novice instructors generate the “activation energy” necessary for a successful IBL classroom. Category 1 small grant applicants are required to select a target course (and IBL materials) for their first foray into IBL, as well as a mentor to guide them through the startup process. Since students are already told that Introduction to Proof is a course where things will be done “differently” than they are used to, this seemed a natural choice for a novice IBLer’s first attempt. Applications were due 4 weeks after I returned from MathFest, and 2 weeks in to my very young teaching career. At the closing talk for our Project NExT workshop, Joe Gallian urged us to “Just say yes.” And so that’s exactly what I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grant application was successful, and as Stan Yoshinobu will tell you, this led to my planning a “Summer of IBL” (cue the Bryan Adams background music). After a year of teaching by the “traditional” lecture approach, I attended (in short succession) the &lt;a href=&#34;http://legacyrlmoore.org/Reports/201506/program.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Legacy of RL Moore conference&lt;/a&gt; in Austin, the IBL Workshop in San Luis Obispo, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maa.org/meetings/mathfest-archive&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MathFest 2015&lt;/a&gt; in Washington, D.C.. Each conference provided me with opportunities to network with experienced IBLers, discuss startup issues with other novice instructors, and to see a different part of the country. The IBL Workshop, in particular, was an important week, intensely focused on getting one-on-one time with practitioners who had taught our target course. The NSF has just awarded a $2.8 million grant, called &lt;a href=&#34;http://theiblblog.blogspot.com/2015/08/announcement-28-million-national.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PRODUCT&lt;/a&gt;, for Cal Poly to expand and continue the IBL Workshop program, and I strongly encourage interested faculty (and high school teachers!) to attend future workshops. I’ll share more in a future post about my specific takeaways from the 2015 edition, but it was, above all else, instrumental in giving me the confidence and courage to take my courses in a new direction. For me, IBL is more than a pedagogical style. It is a supportive community of like-minded individuals focused on doing what we believe is best for our students, and sharing freely the resources that make this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-David Failing&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Commutative, idempotent groupoids and the constraint satisfaction problem</title>
      <link>/publication/2015-algebra-universalis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2015-algebra-universalis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissertation: Commutative, idempotent groupoids and the constraint satisfaction problem</title>
      <link>/publication/2013-dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2013-dissertation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Defense: Commutative, Idempotent Groupoids and The Constraint Satisfaction Problem</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-07-05-phd-defense/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-07-05-phd-defense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Come eat some free food, learn what all the words in the event title mean, and offer moral support! After 5 long years at Iowa State, it&amp;rsquo;s time to graduate so that I can move on to&amp;hellip; more graduate school!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure Theory of CI-Groupoids of Bol-Moufang Type</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-04-28-ams-central/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-04-28-ams-central/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A groupoid identity $p \approx q$ is of Bol-Moufang type if (i) the same 3 variables appear in $p$ and $q$, (ii) one of the variables appears twice in $p$ and $q$, (iii) the remaining two variables appear once in $p$ and $q$, and (iv) the variables appear in the same order in $p$ and $q$. Phillips and Vojtechovsky studied quasigroup and loop varieties defined by one additional identity of Bol-Moufang type, showing that there are exactly 26 and 14 such varieties, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aided by Prover9/Mace4 and the Universal Algebra Calculator, we show that there are exactly eight varieties of commutative, idempotent groupoids defined by one additional identity of Bol-Moufang type. Five of them are congruence meet-semidistributive. We investigate the structure of the variety of commutative, idempotent groupoids satisfying $x(x(yz)) \approx (x(xy))z$, and show that it is the regularization of the variety of squags. We also show that every finite commutative, idempotent, distributive groupoid is a Plonka sum of quasigroups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSP for Commutative, Idempotent Groupoids</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-04-14-ams-western/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2013 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-04-14-ams-western/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A theorem of Bulatov, Jeavons and Krokhin states that when the algebra associated with a core template does not lie in a Taylor variety, then the CSP for that template is NP-complete. In the same paper, the authors conjecture that in all other cases, the corresponding CSP is solvable in polynomial time. Maroti and McKenzie showed that an algebra generates a Taylor variety if and only if it has a $k$-ary weak near-unanimity (WNU) operation for some $k$; this shifts the search for a proof of the algebraic dichotomy conjecture to focus on WNU operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A binary operation is a WNU precisely if it is commutative and idempotent, and a semilattice operation is known to be sufficient for the tractability of an algebra. Using Prover9 and the Universal Algebra Calculator, we investigate several weakenings of associativity and show that they too are sufficient for the tractability of a finite commutative, idempotent groupoid. In particular a finite CI-groupoid has a tractable CSP if it satisfies any of the following identities: $x(y(xz)) \approx x((yx)z)$, $x(y(yz)) \approx ((xy)y)z$, $x(yz) \approx (xy)(xz)$. A key tool is the theory of Plonka sums. Roughly speaking, we prove that a finite Plonka sum of finite algebras lying in a tractable variety is tractable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer-Aided Investigation of Abstract Algebras (Or, The Computer Solved My Thesis Problem...)</title>
      <link>/talk/2013-03-21-mtcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2013-03-21-mtcs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract Algebra is the study of axiomatically defined structures arising from concrete objects, with the aim of establishing properties of those objects. Universal Algebra, loosely construed, is the study of axiom systems for their own sake (e.g. the theory of groups). With the help of automated reasoning tools like Prover9/Mace 4 and the Universal Algebra calculator, we may rapidly generate structures which satisfy a system of axioms, or make (and test) conjectures about the axioms. The talk will be particularly accessible to students currently enrolled in Math 200 and beyond, and possible topics for future undergraduate research will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Prelim: Constraint Satisfaction Problems On Bol-Moufang CI-Groupoids</title>
      <link>/talk/2012-09-20-phd-prelim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2012-09-20-phd-prelim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Come listen to me talk about Constraint Satisfaction Problems and Bol-Moufang Groupoids! Or come heckle me from the back row! Or, just come and eat tasty snacks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Affinely self-generating sets and substitution sequences</title>
      <link>/talk/2008-12-01-isu-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2008 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2008-12-01-isu-seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kimberling defined a self-generating set $S$ of integers as follows: 1 is a member of $S$, and if $x$ is a member of $S$, then $2x$ and $4x - 1$ are in $S$. Nothing else is in $S$. As an REU project, I investigated several interesting properties of the Kimberling set, and its resulting sequences reduced modulo  m  - particularly the case  m  = 2, which yields the Fibonacci word. &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/journals/JIS/VOL10/Garth/garth14.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Garth and Gouge (2007)&lt;/a&gt; proved not only that any of a special class of affinely self-generating sets of integers reduced modulo $m$may be generated by a substitution morphism, but also its characteristic sequence, which turns out to be automatic. The talk will be introductory in nature, and will also discuss some of the open questions posed by Garth and Gouge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Generating Sets, Missing Blocks, and Substitutions</title>
      <link>/talk/2006-03-31-maa-missouri/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2006-03-31-maa-missouri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We generalize the result of Allouche, Shallit, and Skordev regarding the Kimberling sequence, defined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1$ belongs to $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the integer $x$ belongs to $S$, then $2x$ and $4x-1$ are also in $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nothing else is in $S$. Thus:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$S = 1\  2\  3\  4\  6\  7\  8\  11\  12\  14\  15\  16\ldots$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set $T=S-1$, with its first term removed, is both the set of integers whose binary expansions contain no 00 block and the fixed point of the Fibonacci morphism $0\rightarrow01$, $1\rightarrow0$. We expand this result to the natural generalization of the Fibonacci morphism, of the form $0\rightarrow0^n1$, $1\rightarrow0$&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Generating Sets, Missing Blocks, and Substitutions</title>
      <link>/talk/2005-11-12-mako/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2005 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/2005-11-12-mako/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We generalize the result of Allouche, Shallit, and Skordev regarding the Kimberling sequence, defined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1$ belongs to $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the integer $x$ belongs to $S$, then $2x$ and $4x-1$ are also in $S$;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nothing else is in $S$. Thus:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$S = 1\  2\  3\  4\  6\  7\  8\  11\  12\  14\  15\  16\ldots$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set $T=S-1$, with its first term removed, is both the set of integers whose binary expansions contain no 00 block and the fixed point of the Fibonacci morphism $0\rightarrow01$, $1\rightarrow0$. We expand this result to the natural generalization of the Fibonacci morphism, of the form $0\rightarrow0^n1$, $1\rightarrow0$&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduate Coursework</title>
      <link>/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
