<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>podcast | David Failing</title>
    <link>/category/podcast/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/podcast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>podcast</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© David Failing 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu2fefdda865d4d5c2e240ee6c853294a4_26624_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>podcast</title>
      <link>/category/podcast/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>LHRL #57 - DAVID FAILING</title>
      <link>/2017/07/05/lhrl-57-david-failing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/07/05/lhrl-57-david-failing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This podcast first appeared at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liftheavyrunlong.com/lhrl-57-david-failing/&#34;&gt;Lift Heavy Run Long&lt;/a&gt; in July 2017
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click through to the link above to listen, or watch on YouTube: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NJ9m-FoFK_Q&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NJ9m-FoFK_Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Failing is a 31 year old professor of mathematics at Lewis University, near Chicago. Yes, for a brief moment, there were TWO doctors in the LHRL studios. Just a few months after he started running in the fall of 2009, the ultra seed was planted (though it took a while to take hold), and in 2014 he ran his first 50k, followed by a 50 miler in 2015, and his first (and only to date) 100 miler at the Arkansas Traveller in 2016. Above all else, David believes that trail and ultra running allow us to explore the world under our own power, and he wants others to get out and explore however they can (running, hiking, biking, boating…). From October 2017 to October 2018, he will run all six 100 mile trail races in the state of Illinois to raise money for a non-profit (Trails for Illinois) that helps communities benefit economically from their local trails, and also builds and maintains those same trails. Why six 100 milers in a year? Because nobody ever told him he couldn’t. He will be blogging about his training and racing at &lt;a href=&#34;http://trails.davidfailing.com&#34;&gt;http://trails.davidfailing.com&lt;/a&gt;, and asks you to consider even a small donation at &lt;a href=&#34;http://hennepinhundred.causevox.com/davidfailing&#34;&gt;http://hennepinhundred.causevox.com/davidfailing&lt;/a&gt; to support Illinois trails.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Episode 55 - TJM Goes To Veteran&#39;s Acres</title>
      <link>/2017/06/02/episode-55-tjm-goes-to-veteran-s-acres/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/06/02/episode-55-tjm-goes-to-veteran-s-acres/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This podcast first appeared at &lt;a href=&#34;https://tenjunkmiles.libsyn.com/episode-55-tjm-goes-to-veterans-acres&#34;&gt;Ten Junk Miles&lt;/a&gt; in June 2017
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click through to the link above to listen, or find Ten Junk Miles on iTunes, Spotify, or your other favorite podcast app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join Scotty, Rachel Ingle and Kyle Gilman as we go on a road trip to MUDD territory and run at Veteran&amp;rsquo;s Acres and do the first ever totally random sit down podcast in nature. We chat with Mike Farrington (about Squamish) and David Failing (about Math), as well as a whole host of other things in this expiramental and ground breaking show by everyday runners about everyday runners after having a everyday run.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
